Guide to the Nathan Comfort Starr Arthuriana Ephemera Collection, 1915 - 1979
Nathan Comfort Starr Arthuriana Ephemera Collection, 1915-1979
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Starr, Nathan Comfort, 1896-1981.
1000-197
2.1
4, and one volume
Nathan Comfort Starr (1896-1981) was a graduate of Harvard and Oxford Universities. He taught and wrote extensively about the Arthurian legend and Arthurian literature.
The collection contains clippings, correspondence, manuscript and other print materials and ephemera relating to the subject of Arthurian scholarship. Many items were removed from books in the Nathan Comfort Starr Collection of Arthuriana (now held in the Wesleyan University's Special Collections & Archives), and can be cross-referenced with the book's title and call number.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Bequest of Nathan Comfort Starr, 1981.
Historical Note
Nathan Comfort Starr was born in Eau Claire, Wisconsin in 1896. He received degrees from Harvard and Oxford Universities. It was a class at Harvard, taught by G. H. Maynadier, which first piqued Starr's interest in the Arthurian legends. He would go on to teach courses in Arthurian literature and write King Arthur Today: The Arthurian Legend in English and American Literature, 1901-1953, a study of modern Arthurian adaptations. During his career, Starr taught English at Harvard, Radcliffe College, Colgate University, St. John's University, Rollins College, Williams College, and the University of Florida. He was a member of the Grolier Club in New York, and exhibited a number of items from his Arthuriana collection there in 1972. Starr passed away in 1981 at the age of 84.
Collection Overview
The collection contains clippings, correspondence, manuscript and other print materials and ephemera relating to the subject of Arthurian scholarship. Many items were removed from books in the Nathan Comfort Starr Collection of Arthuriana (now held in the Wesleyan University's Special Collections & Archives), and can be cross-referenced with the book's title and call number.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Starr, Nathan Comfort, 1896-1981.; Arthur, King--History and criticism.; Nathan Comfort Starr Collection of Arthuriana.; Arthur, King--In literature.; Arthur, King--Legends.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Individual Items
  - Material (corresp., notes, mss.) relating to 17th annual meeting of Midwest Modern Language Assn., Chicago, 7 November 1975 / follow-up letter 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes and papers from class taught by G. H. Maynadier at Harvard, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notebook of course notes, Arthurian Romances, Harvard (Volume 1)
    This item is shelved in its own enclosure, separately from Box 1.
  - Grolier Club exhibition materials, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Clippings, programs, and brochures that were included as examples; descriptive labels for books included in the exhibition.
- Manuscript Material
  - Manuscript and letter from Karen Rockow, Fall 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Musical comedy script: Sir Gawain & the Green Knight, Gerry ---? (1958) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poem, Carpenter in Camelot, Willard Wattles, 1 April 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lancelot at the Grail Castle, Myra Olstead [published 1965] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sir Tristrem: reflections on romance aesthetics, Mary Hynes-Berry, presented August 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Arthurian legend in the twentieth century: Introduction, Nathan Comfort Starr, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 4 transcripts of Arthurian radio dramas by Ben Aycrigg, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Poem, Arthur, by Stuart James (Rollins) 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arthurian retellings #3 1910-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Arthurian legends: an annotated bibliography: a supplement to the bibliographies of Clark S. Northup, John J. Parry, and Paul A. Brown / [by] Nathan Comfort Starr (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Artorius: a heroic poem in four books and eight episodes by John Heath-Stubbs, Nathan Comfort Starr (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes on 20th century Arthurian works (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The poet's address to a young knight, Nathan Comfort Starr, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Printed Matter
  - Clippings 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clippings 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Four sides of one story, John Updike. New Yorker, 9 October 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Material from production of Dryden-Purcell King Arthur, N.Y., 22 April 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Profile of Helaine Newstead by Morton Hunt. New Yorker, 30 March 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Illustration: Christmas at King Arthur's Court, John Gilbert. Illustrated London News, 10 December 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Wellesley Alumnae Magazine, July 1958. Contains Arthurian pilgrimage, Laura Hibbard Loomis (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Observer Magazine, 6 November 1966. Contains Arthur: the future king, Esther Ronay (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Publications, newsletters – Camelot Research Committee, 1966?-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Program: Metropolitan Opera, Lincoln Center for the Performance Arts, 1970-1971 season Performance of Parzival, 9 April 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Program: The Metropolitan Museum of Art Performance of A King for All Ages: Arthur and the Round Table in Legend and Art, October 9 and 11, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The King Arthur Plates (Box 2, Folder 11)
    3 fully-colored illustrations in envelope. Subscription form for order of collection of 6 porcelain plates bearing Arthurian illustrations.
  - Camelot booklet (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Collectable booklet from stage performances of Camelot. [20] p. with photographs and biographies.
  - Program: Glastonbury Festival, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Brochure: King Arthur's Castle Hotel, Tintagel, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Program: Parsifal Benefit, NY, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Publisher/bookseller advertisements, catalogs, etc. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Prince Valiant comic strips, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ye knights of ye Table Round: being ye inside dope on King Arthur's court, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Program: Parsifal, Teatro Costanzi, Rome, 28 March 1921 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Blank postcards: Arthurian locations: Tintagel and Glastonbury Abbey (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Barnard [College] Reports, Vol. 5, no. 2, December 1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Contains article about performances of Miracles at Glastonbury.
  - The Enchanted Weekend, John MacCormac, in From Unknown Worlds, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Incomplete issue of Famous Funnies, 1948[?] (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes Oaky Doaks, set in King Arthur's time
  - Merlin ou Les contes perdus, Andrée Pragane, ill. Jean Reschofsky (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Steuben Glass Information Bulletin, Vol. 10, no. 4, 31 March 1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Clarification on Excalibur
  - Map: University of Edgestow (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Christian Nurture Stories, Lesson 29: Sir Galahad (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Flyer: Eleventh International Arthurian Congress, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence
  - General Arthurian correspondence, 1952-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ackerman, Robert and Lagorio, Valerie, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brewer, Wilmon, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letter from R.S. Hawker, 7 September 1864 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Heath-Stubbs, John, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lagorio, Valerie, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - McCoy, Dorothy Schuchman, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Poag, James F., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Vinaver, Eugène, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Materials Removed from Starr Book Collection
  - The hero; a study in tradition, myth, and drama: Clipping: obituary of Lord Raglan (author), 15 September 1964, BL325.H46 R3 1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The manual of the Knights of the Round Table Club, A.D. 1720: Clipping: photo with caption regarding Knights of the Round Table Club, 27 October 1947, CR4869 .K5 1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The vision of history in early Britain: from Gildas to Geoffrey of Monmouth: Clipping: review, 23 February 1967, DA1.H33 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arthur and his times: Britain in the Dark Ages: Clipping: review, 24 October 1958, and card from Bodleian Library, Oxford, DA135.L53 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arthur: Roman Britain's last champion: Clipping: review of Hibbert, C., The search for King Arthur, 16 April 1970, DA135.S16 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The legendary history of Britain: Dust jacket flaps, DA140.G37 T3 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Historia regum Britanniæ of Geoffrey of Monmouth: Clipping: review, 14 November 1929; Clipping: response letter, 28 November 1929; and publisher's advertisement, DA140 .G45 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The age of Arthur: Clipping: review, 27 August 1973; Clipping: review, 21 September 1973, DA145.M56 1973b (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - From Caesar to Arthur: Clipping: review, 5 February 1960, DA152 .A8 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The conquest of Wessex in the sixth century: Clipping: review, 12 March 1954; card from Bodleian Library, Oxford; dust jacket flaps, DA152.C7 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The black horsemen: Clipping: advertisement, DA152.W53 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Camelot and the vision of Albion: Clipping: review, 1972?; postcard advertisement, DA152.5.A7 A79 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - King Arthur in Cornwall: 3 postcards of Tintagel, blank, DA152.5.A7 D5 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Flores historarium: Handwritten notes on condition of volume, DA220.M438 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Camden's Britannia.. .: 2 facsimile Illustrations, labeled as being by Wm. Daniell, R.A., circa 1814-1824; plate: Sterling a principal town in Scotland; printed strip of photographs of various locations (in Stirling?); Handwritten notes; 2 printed bookseller's descriptions, DA610.C35 G52 1695 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Arthurian sites in the west: Photocopied leaf: Tintagel & Castle Dore, Monday 18th August, DA670.W49 R3 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - King Arthur's Avalon: Clipping: review, 6 December 1957; clipping: article, 21 May 1958; publisher's advertisement, DA690.G45 A8 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Official guide to Glastonbury: Postcard of Glastonbury, addressed to NCS, otherwise blank, DA690.G45 B5 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Glastonbury legends: Clipping: review 21 December 1967, DA690.G45 T7 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Myth or legend?: Clipping: advertisement; dust jacket flap, GR73.M9 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Parsifal 1960: 2 ticket stubs: Festspiele Bayreuth 1960 performance of Parsifal; clipping: review of P.Turing, New Bayreuth, and Wolfgang Wagner zum 50 Geburtstag, 11 December 1969, ML410.W2 B26 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Oxford Union Society: Leaf from bookseller's catalog: Wm. Smith & Son, hand-dated, 1952, ND2731.O9 H9 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Form and meaning in Medieval romance: Letter from Eugene Vinaver to NCS, 24 December 1966, PB6.M5 1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - On the study of Celtic literature: 2 postcards depicting Irish saints, blank, PB1096.A6 1867 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Gododdin: Clipping: review 9 September 1969, PB2273.A73 J3 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Medieval miscellany: Clipping: review 10 March 1966; publisher's advertisement and order form; letter from Eugène Vinaver to NCS, 16 April 1965; Letter from Vinaver to NCS, 11 July 1965, PC14.V48 1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Chrestomathie du Moyen Age: Leaf from textbook: 1921-1922 Harvard University Romance Philology 3 (translation exercises), PC2825.P3 1919 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Jaufry the knight...: Letter from Morris Saffron to NCS, undated, PC3328.J3 A21 1857a (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - An index of the Arthurian names in Middle English: Letter from Bill Ackerman to NCS, 21 December 1968, PE1660.A23 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - The rose miraculous: 3 postcards of Glastonbury, blank, PN56.G57 1924 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Arthur of Albion: Postcard from Patricia McKenzie to NCS; Letter from NCS to the Editor of the London Times Literary Supplement, 8 October 1961; Hand-written notes; Clipping: review 15 September 1961; Leaf from MLA Quarterly Vol. 23, No. 4, December 1962, PN57.A6 B3 1961 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The holy Grail: Hand-written notes, PN57.G7 W3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Guinevere: a study of her abductions: Letter from Deborah Webster to NCS, 31 October 1957; letter from Webster to NCS, 26 March 1960, PN57.G85 W4 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The tryst beneath the tree: Letter from Helaine Newstead to NCS, 22 July 1954, PN57.T8 N49 1956 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Studies in medieval and Renaissance literature: Clipping: review, 14 July 1966, PN681.L4 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Arthuriana: Letter from H. J. B. Gray to NCS, 4 September 1929; Leaf: With the compliments of Professor E. Vinaver, PN685.A7 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - King Arthur and his knights of the Round Table: Clipping: review, 27 November 1953, PN685.A7 1953 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - The education of the hero in Arthurian romance: Flyer: Medieval and Renaissance Fete sponsored by the Institute for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, City College, NY, 1971, PN685.C6 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Arthurian legend in the literatures of the Spanish peninsula: Publisher's press copy announcement, PN685.E6 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Wales and the Arthurian legend: Clipping: review, 21 December 1956, PN685.L64 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - La légende Arthurienne: Clipping: review, 25 July 1952, PN685.M3 L4 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Arthurian torso: Clipping: review, 6 February 1959, PN685.W5 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Arthurian romance and modern poetry and music: Clipping: review, 18 January 1941, PN686.A7 N5 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Bran the Blessed in Arthurian romance: Letter from Helaine Newstead to NCS, 11 October (year unknown); letter from Newstead to NCS, 13 November 1948; letter from Newstead to NCS, 23 April 1952; letter from Newstead to NCS, 4 September 1970; leaf from publisher's catalog, PN686.B7 N4 1939 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - The ancient secret: Letter from Myra Olstead to NCS, 24 June 1957; clipping: review, 12 February 1954, PN686.G7 A6 1955 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - The Grail from Celtic myth to Christian symbol: Leaf: review, 1965; letter from Roger Loomis to NCS; dust jacket flap, PN686.G7 L6 1963 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Mystic gleams from the holy Grail: Clipping: advertisement, PN686.G7 R6 1948 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Selections from the prose Merlin: Clipping: review, 8 November 1930, PN686.M5 C89 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - The Tristan legend: Publisher's advertisement/order form, PN686.T7 E4 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Britain in Medieval French literature, 1100-1500: Clipping: review, 28 December 1956; dust jacket flap, PQ155.G7 R5 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Table des noms propres...: Publisher's advertisement/sample page, PQ155.N2 F55 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - A study of the pseudo-map cycle of Arthurian romance: Publisher's advertisement/order form, PQ203.C3 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Fabliaux: Notecard, description of item, PQ1319.L52 1796 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Cliges: Letter from Jean Frappier to NCS, 1965 (reply written on back), PQ1445.C6 F73 1958 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Lancelot and Guenevere: Clipping: advertisement, PQ1445.L5 C7 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Continuations of the Old French Perceval: Letter from William Roach to NCS, 10 January 1954; letter from Roach to NCS, 15 February 1960; letter from Roach to NCS, 28 January 1966; letter from Roach to NCS, 2 November 1972; clipping: review, 23 February 1957, PQ1445.P2 C6 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Ywain: the knight of the lion: Compliments of the publishers notecard; postcard from Robert Ackerman, 1958, PQ1447.E5 A2 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Chrétien, Troyes, and the Grail: Clipping: review, 1959, PQ1448.H75 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Arthurian tradition and Chrétien de Troyes: Letter from Roger S. Loomis to NCS, 27 April 1959; letter from Loomis to NCS, 11 September 1966; letter from Dorothy B. Loomis to NCS, 18 October 1966; clipping: obituary: picture of Loomis, text of Slip Madigan, 12 October 1966; Clipping: review, 20 January 1950, PQ1448.L6 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Lumiére du Graal: Publisher's advertisement, PQ1472.N4 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Lorgaireacht an tSoidhigh Naomhtha: Clipping: review, 8 January 1954, PQ1475.A64 1953 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Sir Lancelot of the lake: Clipping: review, 17 October 1929, PQ1489.L2 E56 1929 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Lancelot du lac 1488: Clipping: review, 17 December 1976; broadside: Arthurian romances, a Scolar Press facsimile (advertisement), PQ1489.L2 S38 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Merlin 1498: Publisher's advertisement/order form; illustrated bookmark; Church of the Epiphany operating fund report of the treasurer for April 1975, PQ1496.M4 1975 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - The tale of Balain: Publisher's advertisement: The tale of Balain / The romance of Tristan and Isolt, PQ1496.M422 E5 1972 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Les prophecies de Merlin: Leaf from publisher's catalog: Herbert Reichner, Stockbridge, Mass., 1959, PQ1496.M44 1926 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - La mort le roi Artu: Letter from Jean Frappier to NCS, 17 January 1962, PQ1496.M75 1954 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - The Didot Perceval: Clipping: advertisement; lLetter from William Roach to NCS, 27 January 1954, PQ1501.P33 1941 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Le roman de Laurin: Advertisement, PQ1532.R3 1960 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Le roman de Laurin: Letter from Lewis Thorpe to NCS, 10 May 1973, PQ1532.R63 T5 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Le roman de Tristan par Béroul: Clipping: review, 8 December 1972; Letter from Janet Caulkins to NCS, 5 February 1974, PQ1537.A1 1965 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - La grant ystoire de Monsignor Tristan Li Bret: Clipping: review, 30 May 1942, PQ1541.A15 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Tristan 1489: The Scolar Newsletter, No. 11, 31 May 1977, PQ1541.A16 1976 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - The meaning of pechié.. .: Photocopied review, 1972, signed by author [Janet H. Caulkins], PQ1543.C8 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - La forêt de Morois: Letter from Eugène Vinaver to NCS, 12 June 1970, with response, 20 June 1970, PQ1543.V47 F6 1968 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - The tale of Gargantua and King Arthur: Clipping: review, 8 December 1932, PQ1625.G35 A7 1932 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - The Arthurian legend in Italian literature: Clipping: review, 25 June 1931, PQ4053.A7 G3 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Arthurian legend in the seventeenth century: Publisher's advertisement for Fagin, N. Bryllion, William Bartram: interpreter of the American Landscape, PR438.A7 B7 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - King Arthur today: Clipping: Newspaper announcement for Grolier Club exhibition, The Flower of Kings (Arthuriana), PR479.A7 S7 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Sir Gawain and the Green Knight: Clipping: review, 25 January 1941, PR1119.A2 no. 210 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - English and Scottish popular ballads: Letter from George L. Kittredge to NCS, 25 February 1927, PR1181.C5 1904a (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Bishop Percy's folio manuscript: Clipping: Letter to the editor (London Times) from P.G. Thomas, Bishop Percy and the Scottish Ballads, 4 July 1929; Clipping: Responses to Thomas' letter, 11 July 1929, PR1181.P45 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - The complete works of the Gawain-poet: Clipping: review, 21 July 1966, PR1203.G36 1965 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Layamon's Brut: Letter from Robert Ackerman to NCS, 6 October 1972; Neuphilologische mitteilungen, Vol. 73, 1972: Sir Frederic Madden and Medieval Scholarship, signed by Ackerman (author), PR2021.M3 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Selections from Layamon's Brut: Receipt from publisher, 6 December 1964, PR2024.B7 1963 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - The most ancient and famous history... [Morte Darthur]: Hand-written note about condition of volume, PR2040 1634 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Winchester Malory: Photographic note card from Nina Starr; Poetica, Autumn 1977: Caxton's Malory, signed by Shunichi Noguchi (author); Advertisement/order form for A Concordance to the works of Sir Thomas Malory; Letter from Basil Blackwell to NCS, 1 March 1977, PR2040 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Le morte d'Arthur: Publisher's advertisement/order form for various Caxton reprints, PR2040 1976a (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Le morte d'Arthur: Clipping: Article about Caxton stamps, 10 October 1976; Flyer: A Caxton Celebration 16 April 1977, Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, City College, NY; Publisher's advertisement, PR2041.S66 1889 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The works of Sir Thomas Malory: Letter from Eugène Vinaver to NCS, 16 November 1948; clipping: review, 18 February 1977; postcard of Christ Church, Oxford, from Bob Nikish, 5 October 1976; Publisher's advertisement/order form for various Caxton reprints; letter from Vinaver to NCS, 19 December 1968, PR2041.V5 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - King Arthur and his knights: Hand-written notes, PR2042.V5 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Malory's Le morte d'Arthur: Clipping: review, 2 April 1964, PR2043.B3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Arthur Pendragon of Britain: Dust jacket flap; clipping: review, 15 August 1943; clipping: review, 25 December 1943, PR2043.D6 1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The book of King Arthur and his noble knights: Postcard of Winchester College, blank, PR2043.M16 1902 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Le morte d'Arthur: 3 publisher's advertisements, PR2043.P6 1921 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The birth, life, and acts of King Arthur...: Postcard of Beardsley Morte d'Arthur illustration from Nancy [no last name], 1976, PR2043.R5 1909 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The morte Darthur: Hand-written notes, PR2043.S3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Essays on Malory: Clipping: review, 21 November 1963, PR2045.B4 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sir Thomas Malory: Clipping: review, 20 December 1928, PR2045.H5 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Malory's originality: Hand-written notes; Letter from William H. Matchett, 22 January 1965; Clipping: review, 1965; Manuscript: review by NCS; Offprint: NCS review; Offprint: review by Richard L. Greene, signed, PR2045.L8 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Le morte Darthur of Sir Thomas Malory...: Clipping: Newspaper article Northwestern professor seeks Holy Grail origin, 19 January 1927; Letter from Vida Scudder to Frederica B.G. Howell, 4 January 1937; Letter from Scudder to Howell, 14 May 1937[?], PR2045.S5 1921 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 'Wade,' 'Dryvande,' and 'Gotelake'...: Letter from Toshiyuki Takamiya to NCS, 16 October 1974, PR2045.T35 1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Malory: Invitation to presentation of Medieval miscellany to E. Vinaver, Univ. of Manchester, 18 June 1965, PR2045.V5 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Malory: style and vision...: Receipt from Yale University Press, 8 August 1978, PR2048.L3 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The ill-framed knight: Clipping: review, 30 November 1967; Speculum: Review: The ill-framed knight.. ., 1968, signed by Robert Ackerman (author), PR2049.M3 1966 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Middle English humorous tales in verse: Brochure: St. Botolph's Tower, Boston, England, PR2064.M3 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - The Awntyrs off Arthure...: Letter from NCS to H.P. Kraus, 3 November 1971, PR2065.A8 1969 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Story of Sir Gawain and the Green Knight: Clipping: review, 17 June 1944, PR2065.G3 1944 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - From Cuchulainn to Gawain: Letter from Sarah Brewer to NCS, PR2065.G305 B7 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Art and tradition in Sir Gawain...: Letter from Roy F. Leslie to NCS, 12 October 1978, PR2065.G31 B4 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - A reading of Sir Gawain...: Clipping: review, 1966; Shell Books advertisement, PR2065.G31 B8 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Critical studies of Sir Gawain...: Manuscript: Sir Gawain and the Medieval school of comedy; Attached letter from Roy F. Leslie to NCS, 29 August 1978, PR2065.G31 H6 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - The Gawain-poet: Clipping: review, 31 May 1957, PR2065.G31 S3 (Box 4, Folder 28)